Doctor: When was it she last walked?
Gentlewoman: For two nights together,
I have seen her rise from her bed, throw her nightgown upon her, unlock her closet,
take forth paper, fold it, write upon it, read it, afterwards seal it, and again return to bed;
yet all this while in a most fast sleep.
Doctor: Besides her walking and other actual performances,
what, at any time, have you heard her say?
Gentlewoman: That, which I will not report after her.
Doctor: You may to me and ‘tis most meet you should.
Gentlewoman: Neither to you, nor any one, having no witness to confirm my speech.
Lo you, here she comes − this is her very guise, and, upon my life, fast asleep.
Observe her and stand close.
Doctor: How came she by that light?
Gentlewoman: She has light by her, continually, ‘tis her command.
Doctor: You see her eyes are open.
Gentlewoman: Aye, but their sense is shut.
Doctor: What is it she does now?
Gentlewoman: It is an accustomed action with her.
Lady Macbeth: Yet here’s a spot.
Out, damned spot − out, I say.
One − two − why, then, ’tis time to do it − Hell is murky.
Fie, my lord, fie, a soldier, and afeard?
What need we fear who knows this, when none can call our power to account?
Yet who would have thought the old man to have had so much blood in him?
Doctor: Do you mark that?
Lady Macbeth: The Thane of Fife had a wife − where is she now?
What, will these hands ne’er be clean?
No more o’ that, my lord, no more o’ that − you mar all with this starting.
Doctor: Go to, go to: you have known what you should not.
Gentleman: She has spoke what she should not, I am sure of that.
Lady Macbeth: Here’s the smell of the blood still
− all the perfumes of Arabia will not sweeten this little hand. Oh, oh, oh!
Doctor: What a sigh is there. The heart is sorely charged.
Gentlewoman: I would not have such a heart in my bosom, for the dignity of the whole body.
Doctor: This disease is beyond my practice;
yet I have known those which have walked in their sleep, who have died holily in their beds.
Lady Macbeth: Wash your hands, put on your nightgown, look not so pale:
I tell you yet again, Banquo’s buried;
he cannot come out on’s grave.
Doctor: Even so?
Lady Macbeth: To bed, to bed − there’s knocking at the gate − come,
come,
come.
Give me your hand.
What’s done cannot be undone.
To bed,
to bed,
to bed!
Doctor: Foul whisperings are abroad.
Unnatural deeds do breed unnatural troubles:
infected minds to their deaf pillows will discharge their secrets.
More needs she the divine than the physician − God, God forgive us all.
Look after her, remove from her the means of all annoyance, and still keep eyes upon her.
So, good night, my mind she has mated, and amazed my sight.
I think, but dare not speak.
Gentlewoman: Good night, good doctor.